
  
  
    
      Some of the strongest critics of our welfare system are the people who
      have become dependent on it.
      Their complaint: the system discourages working because unemployment
      provides benefits that many entry-level jobs don't include.
      That's where you --and Goodwill --come in. We help people train for
      and find jobs that make it possible for them to get off of welfare. Last
      year, Goodwill placed 511 people in jobs, more than double the number we
      placed in 1993.
      While the debate on welfare reform is gathering like a storm at sea,
      the people who need jobs are floundering. We need your support to
      continue getting people off of public assistance.
      Welfare is not the answer. And welfare reform is an uncertain solution
      with an unknown starting date. Goodwill works. Right now.
      Please give the largest gift you can to Goodwill today.
      Sincerely,
      Jack Dustman Chairman
    
  
