
  
  
    
      June 26, 1995
      Dear Friend:
      This is not newsletter. It is a fund-raising appeal.
      But there's no reason why we shouldn't share good news at the same
      time. Federal, state and local governments are freezing or withdrawing
      much-needed funding sources for people who are truly in need. In spite of
      that, Pleasant Run Children's Homes, with the help of hundreds of
      volunteers and others who really care, continues to make a significant
      impact on the futures of families and kids in need of help.
      We all hear about today's increases in neglect, abuse and abandonment
      of those who can't fight back: children. Yet few of us hear enough about
      kids who live through these adversities and do make the grade.
      The positive side. These are special children. They come into a
      Pleasant Run program... whether it's for therapeutic help in their own
      homes (which nurtures whole families), through foster care families or in
      the familial surroundings of our residential homes.
      For some, it's a matter of weeks or months; for others, it's years.
      They leave Pleasant Run, generally, ready and able to contribute to
      society. We're proud of our children and all that they overcome.
      We are a not-for-profit, multi-service agency. We wouldn't exist if
      the need weren't there. The numbers of children who deserve our services
      are rising... as quickly as our programs can grow to serve them.
      Please help us help them. Pleasant Run Children's Homes... "where good
      kids get better."
      Sincerely,
      Mary Roth Tom Hirschauer
    
  
