
  
  
    
      Dear Friends of Pleasant Run:
      The holiday season is the time of year when we're all busy buying
      gifts, baking goodies, decorating our homes and making arrangements to be
      with family and friends. This is the time of year when we give thanks for
      the warmth and love that surrounds us. And this time of year is an
      occasion to remember those not as fortunate as we are.
      Pleasant Run cares for at-risk children and families. We do this
      through a wide range of programs including community- based, therapeutic
      foster care, group homes and our treatment center. Many of the children
      are victims of abuse or live in unstable homes.
      Today we are asking you to take a few minutes to consider making a
      contribution to Pleasant Run to help the 1,500 children families we care
      for. Many of the children have no homes; no memories of joy from past
      holidays. Others are from families that are struggling to provide a
      healthy, happy environment but don't have the resources to make it
      possible. Your contribution will make a difference in a child's life. It
      may help a family stay together. It can certainly make happy holiday
      memories.
      A gift to Pleasant Run means the children in our care will have
      presents to open. A gift means a family will have a holiday meal, cooking
      utensils to prepare the meal and dishes to serve it on. Your gift will go
      beyond the holiday season. It can help purchase clothing, school
      supplies, books and educational tools throughout the year.
      
      Please take a few minutes to mail a donation to Pleasant run. Let our
      families and children know that you want them to have the same kinds of
      memories of the holidays you will have.
      We wish you and your family a new year full of joy and love.
      Sincerely,
      Mary Roth Executive Director
    
  
