
  
  
    
      November 27, 1995
      Dear Friend:
      What kind of people benefit by your contribution to Pleasant Run
      Children's Homes?
      Little ones, like Baby Jessica, caught in the struggle between
      adoptive and birth parents. Older kids, like Tracy and Kerry, left
      homeless after a recent murder-suicide in Indianapolis claimed Mom and
      Dad. Young adults, like Mary T., a jobless mother of three, trying
      desperately to keep her kids out of trouble in a crime-ridden
      neighborhood. Real people!
      There are thousands more. Families are being torn apart, and too
      often, children are the victims. Kids like Tommie J., made a ward of the
      court because of repeated beatings by an alcoholic father; Alice, sent to
      a group home to get help because of severe behavior disorders; and John
      H., a recovering alcoholic, rebuilding a relationships with his family so
      they can live together again.
      Pleasant Run Children's Homes began serving children nearly 130 years
      ago. Then the task was to help children who lost parents in the Civil
      War. Today, we serve children and families with a multitude of problems:
      emotional, physical, psychological and sexual abuse. Some come from
      families where, through therapy, there is hope for reunification. For
      others, "families" are the counselors are housemates at the group homes
      where they live.
      The biggest tragedy is that the problems don't go away; they only
      grow. In 1994 Pleasant Run served 346 children and 125 families. In 1995
      we will serve over 850 children and 340 families. In 1996, these figures
      will triple. The children and families who come to Pleasant Run are given
      the opportunity to become happy, loving, and productive members of our
      society. They welcome the chance to belong, to become self- sufficient,
      to regain their self-esteem and confidence. Often it is a long, hard
      struggle, but the results are well worth it.
      For Pleasant Run to continue to serve abused and neglected children
      and their families, we need your support. The Funding sources are
      shrinking, but the needs grow explosively. Please "help good kids get
      better" by sending us a contribution today. Your gift will give children
      and families hope for improved tomorrows.
      Sincerely,
      Mary Roth
    
  
