
  
  
    
      July 11, 1997
      Name Address City, State Zip
      Dear Mr./Mrs. Name:
      We need your help in continuing the work of Jameson Camp.
      Jameson is a not-for-profit agency established in 1928 to serve the
      youth of central Indiana who have special needs. The camp offers summer
      residential programs for children from ages 7-17, and continues contact
      with the campers and their families with special overnight and weekend
      follow-up events during the school year.
      All children who attend the camp are referred by social workers,
      doctors, teachers, counselors, and other professionals. Many of the
      children have learning disabilities, behavioral problems, or come from
      economically distressed families. The goal of our organized camping
      experience is to improve the total health of the children socially,
      emotionally, and physically.
      This year Jameson Camp is planning an Inaugural fund-raising event:
      The Jameson Grill! This event is designed to be fun for campers, their
      families, friends of the camp, neighbors, staff, and anyone interested in
      finding out more about Jameson. In short, Fun for Everyone!
      The family-friendly event, September 20, 1997, will include a hog
      roast, activities for kids and adults, prizes for activities, and a small
      raffle. Lucky attendees can go home with a great prize. This is where we
      need your help.
      Can you help support this wonderful event by furnishing any type of
      products or services that can be used as prizes for our activities or as
      a raffle prize? Your contribution will help with funding so Jameson Camp
      can continue providing the year-round camping experience that gives kids
      a chance to create dreams.
      Enclosed is a form you can complete and return to us in the
      postage-paid envelope. Or, you can fax us at 241-2760, or e-mail,
      icfundrzr@aol.com. Your quick response will help us begin organizing our
      prizes. After we receive your commitment, we will contact you about
      picking up your contribution. If you have any questions, please call me
      at 241-2661.
      We appreciate your support of our first event of this type.
      Sincerely,
      Pat Bray Director of Development
      Help Blaze The Trail -- 1997 Jameson Camp Thank you for your last
      Annual Fund Gift!
    
  
