
  
  
    
      Come one, Come all to the Inaugural Jameson Grill
      The only fund raising event in the world where you can bring your
      entire family, other employees, or maybe even your neighbors.
      Saturday, September 20,1997, from 2:00 p.m. until 7:00 p.m., marks a
      special day, as Jameson Camp will hold its first ever Jameson Grill. A
      fund raiser dedicated to you and your family having fun!!
      For this event, when you purchase a corporate picnic table, you will
      be able to bring 16 people. (and if you need room for a couple of more,
      we can swing that too!)
      The Grill will feature enough activities that you and your kids will
      have a tough time deciding what to do. From basketball, kickball,
      volleyball, archery, crafts, an egg toss, and even a walk through our
      creek, you will have plenty to do to get you good and hungry.
      Hungry, you bet! We'll prepare a hog roast and hot dogs for the kids,
      with all the fixings.
      In addition, we will have soft drinks and a raffle, so that you can
      walk home with a great prize!
      The Jameson Grill has been designed to be nothing but fun for you,
      your family, employees, and maybe even your neighbors.
      Join in this wonderful event and help Jameson Camp continue to provide
      the year-round support that gives kids a chance to create dreams.
      Simply fill out the enclosed card, and we will see you at the
      Grill!
      One of our volunteers will be contacting you soon.
      Questions? Call Pat Bray at 241-2661 or e-mail, jcfundrzr@aol.com
      
    
  
