
  
  
    
      June 10, 1997
      Name Address City, ST Zip
      Dear Mrs. Name,
      Confidence. An understanding that, above anything else, success
      requires genuine effort, a willingness to set challenging goals. Caring
      about others.
      These are the attributes we want all children to have. You help
      Jameson campers reach for them. If these special children are to become
      the adults we all need them to be, we have to lead them in the right
      direction right now.
      Jameson points the way for children who need that extra hand and I
      hope you'll continue your support this year. You're last gift of $50.00
      helped make it possible for us to provide guidance, encouragement and fun
      to nearly 400 Indianapolis area children. And not just during the summer,
      but throughout the year.
      What has your support of our campers meant to them and what have they
      been able to accomplish because you care?
      The best indicator I can give you of the positive effect our
      year-round contact has is the growth in and deeds of the Youth Leadership
      teens. In just the past few years this program has grown from a few kids
      and a few extra activities to a team of almost 60 young adults taking on
      real projects. YL teens will make J.C. juniors happen again this year for
      7 and 8 year old campers. A five day camp, J.C. juniors introduces
      at-risk children to Jameson two years earlier than we could previously
      reach them. That means we now have the opportunity to be a stable,
      positive and important part of each child's life for an entire
      decade.
      The teens have also decided to raise money to provide camperships for
      other campers because they know what Jameson has meant to them. And their
      activities aren't isolated to Jameson. The teens have undertaken a
      volunteer project to regularly visit with sick children at a local
      hospital.
      Please consider renewing your gift today. The kids need your
      leadership now more than ever. If you can increase your last donation, we
      would appreciate that show of support for the campers and their efforts
      to overcome obstacles and create successful lives.
      Thank you again for helping point the way.
      Sincerely,
      Julie Marsh, Executive Director
      P.S. You make it possible for us to help special kids with learning
      disabilities, behavior problems and economic disadvantages to gain the
      confidence required to put genuine effort into achieving real goals. I
      hope you'll continue -- and if possible increase - your support for these
      great kids.
    
  
