
  
  
    
      July 25,1997
      Dear Name,
      What a Summer!
      And we're just getting started!
      I hope you'll consider continuing your support of Jameson's special
      campers by renewing your last gift of $ xxx. I can tell you we need your
      help now as much as ever before.
      All of our Six summer camping sessions are booked to capacity (and,
      truth be told, with maybe one our two extra returning campers squeezed
      in) and we have a waiting list of 60 children who are hoping to come if a
      spot should open. Many more camper referrals are coming from new
      organizations such as school social-workers and family counseling
      agencies. It seems summer options aren't readily available for troubled
      kids whose families have limited incomes, so we're doing all we can to
      make Jameson available.
      That "we" includes the Youth Leadership teens. These 60 or so campers
      have takenon a fund raiser with a goal of raising $16,000 for
      camperships. Two of them told me yesterday that as a group they decided
      they had to earn the right to ask others for help by accomplishing
      something real to help themselves. And that's from kids many people see
      as a problem.
      Even after the summer sessions come to a close, Jameson campers will
      take part in year-round programs designed to keep that positive contact
      with peers and role models alive and important. We've scheduled more than
      15 follow-up camper weekends beginning in September and going around till
      next summers camping season.
      Please, consider renewing your support of these great kids today.
      Sincerely,
      Julie Marsh Executive Director
      P.S. We know our follow-up weekends are going to be better attended
      than ever this fall and winter. If you can give a little more to help
      meet this increased expense we would appreciate your support.
      
    
  
