
  
  
    
      January 5, 1997
      Name Address City, ST Zip
      Dear Bill:
      This is the time of year when our thoughts turn to ways to do things
      differently, things that will make our lives better and improve the
      quality of our life. As you begin that process this year, I would like to
      ask you to consider helping young people in Marion County toward more
      positive youth development by becoming a supporter of the Marion County
      Commission on Youth, Inc.
      MCCOY Inc., originally founded as a government agency but re-organized
      in 1993 as an independent not-for-profit, is a county-wide youth services
      coordinating, planning, and convening agency. Its purpose is to encourage
      collaboration and cooperation between the various agencies, programs, and
      systems that serve our community's youth. In addition to that
      behind-the-scenes role, MCCOY has taken an out-front role in developing a
      Summer Bus Pass, neighborhood youth councils, and the We Value Youth
      information line. It is our goal that every young person in Marion County
      have access to the programs and services that can best assist them in
      their growth toward a positive adulthood.
      I am hopeful that you as an individual and Meridian Insurance as a
      corporation might consider becoming sustaining supporters of MCCOY. I
      have enclosed a packet of information about MCCOY and its work as well as
      an application with various options for supporting the youth of our
      community.
      I obviously can't tell the whole story of MCCOY in a single letter but
      I hope this provides an overview of the scope of our work. I will call
      you in a few weeks to discuss your level of interest. Please consider
      joining together with your fellow citizens in support of the work of the
      Marion County Commission on Youth.
      Sincerely,
      John Brandon Executive Director
    
  
