
  
  
    
      August 4, 1999
      Name Address City, ST Zip
      The goal of MCCOY, Inc. has been to make a difference. In 1998, MCCOY,
      Inc. led two efforts that, we believe, will help our community continue
      to take the steps necessary to help all young people grow up and develop
      well.
      Participants in the Youth Outcomes Educational Initiative identified
      three goals for all our youth to obtain: economic self-sufficiency,
      healthy family, social relationships, and involvement in the community. A
      short time later, the Community Youth Mapping Project sent 55 young
      people out into the community to identify the resources they need to grow
      up well: caring adults, safe places to go, and positive things to do.
      One group of adults and one group of youth, through two very different
      processes, have arrived at the same conclusion; our community still has
      much to do if we are to help ALL of your youth successfully develop into
      the responsible, productive adults who will our community in the
      future.
      As a provider of youth services, MCCOY, Inc. is here to support your
      valuable efforts to develop young people. Recently, through a lot of hard
      work and alliances with organizations like yours, some steps have been
      taken in our community that will help young people continue to be
      involved in positive activities. One, IndyGo in April adopted a
      much-needed policy that all young people under the age of 19 may ride on
      their buses at half the normal fare all year long. Two, funding was made
      available this summer for youth organizations and churches to conduct
      positive youth programming on Saturday evenings. Through the youth
      mapping process, it was confirmed that the positive opportunities for
      youth on weekend evenings were lacking. That need is being met.
      As it has been an exciting year for all of us, MCCOY, Inc. cannot do
      its part without the support of organizations like yours. Annually, we
      ask several of our youth serving organizations to join us in our effort
      to help young people grow up well in Indianapolis. Enclosed is a donation
      card that will enable you to make Indianapolis a great place for ALL of
      us to live. If you have any questions or concerns at any time, please do
      not hesitate to call me at 921-1288.
      Sincerely,
      John F. Brandon, President MCCOY, Inc.
    
  
