
  
  
    
      August 6, 1998
      Dear Friend:
      Adolescence. It is a pivotal time in the life of a young girl-when
      small changes in her behavior, or the choices she makes, can affect her
      future. It's hard enough for her to make good decisions when she's
      surrounded by support. It's even harder when she isn't.
      Big Sisters helps fill that void by matching caring, responsible adult
      volunteers with at-risk girls, ages 8-14. A Big Sister is a mentor, a
      friend and a role model, helping a young girl to develop the
      self-confidence and life skills necessary to become a responsible,
      productive and successful adult. Your $1,000 contribution can put a
      mentor in a child's life-and hope in a child's future.
      The results of an 18-month study completed by Public/Private Ventures
      showed that children participating in one-to-one Big Sister and Big
      Brother matches for just one year, reduced first time drug use by 46%;
      lowered school absenteeism by 52%; cut aggressive behavior by 33%;
      enhanced school performance; and improved relations with family and
      friends.
      This is positive proof that Big Sisters one-to-one mentoring program
      helps change lives. Today, we are offering you the opportunity to help
      change a life. By contributing $1,000 you can support one match for one
      year. This money maintains the infrastructure that fosters and supports
      the development of effective relationships. This includes a volunteer
      screening process, orientation, training and ongoing supervision and
      support by a professional staff.
      As a Matchmaker you will receive a description of "your match" and be
      identified as a Matchmaker on a plaque in the Big Sisters office, in the
      agency newsletter and annual report.
      Today Big Sisters serves over 1,000 girls in central Indiana. But for
      each girl served, more are left unserved. Over 235 girls are currently
      waiting for a Big Sister. Imagine the difference the community could make
      if each congregation pledged its support of one Big Sisters match!
      I encourage you to Join me in presenting this matchmaker challenge to
      your congregation.
      Sincerely,
      Dr. Linda McCoy Pastor, THE GARDEN A Blossom of St. Luke's United
      Methodist Church
    
  
