
  
  
    
      July30,1999
      Name Address City, ST Zip
      Dear Mr. Ratcliff:
      CCI is a federation of 13 neighborhood-based multi-service centers
      whose mission is to identify and meet the human service needs of
      residents throughout Marion County in the most effective, efficient and
      comprehensive way possible. In 1998, we served a total of 31,484
      low-income individuals through job training and placement assistance,
      youth and senior programming, family counseling, emergency assistance,
      and much more.
      As you can see from the enclosed map, your Target store is located in
      the heart of four of our service areas. The centers that serve these
      areas, Mary Rigg Neighborhood Center, Hawthorne Community Center,
      Southwest Multi-Service Center, and Christamore House, have teamed up to
      run an exciting job readiness program for 14 and 15 year old area
      residents called the Summer Enrichment Program. Between June 21 and
      August 31, 45 youth will spend 20 hours a week developing life management
      and work ethic skills, learning the computer, visiting area colleges, and
      interacting with guest speakers. The end result will be kids who have a
      better understanding of and vision for their own future, be it college or
      a career.
      The Summer Enrichment Program will conclude with a celebration that
      includes family and friends. We would like to offer our youth a small
      reward for their participation by presenting them with gift certificates
      from Target. Therefore, we are asking you to donate 45, $10 gift
      certificates that can be used toward the purchase of school supplies or
      clothing, in the total amount of $450. In return, we will recognize
      Target as a sponsor during our event and in the event program.
      Target is well known for it's support of the community, and we believe
      that the Summer Enrichment Program represents your interests and concerns
      quite well. I will be happy to supply any additional information you may
      need and thank you for your consideration of our request. We look forward
      to hearing from you.
      Sincerely,
      Valery De Long Director of Development
    
  
