
  
  
    
      October 7, 1996
      Name Address City, ST Zip
      Dear Name:
      In the summer of 1993, the Marion County Commission on Youth began
      what can best be described as a "new era" in its history. MCCOY was
      reorganized as an independent, not-for-profit agency, separate from local
      government. It retained, however, the same mission with which it had been
      charged from its inception: to serve as a catalyst for effective,
      coordinated, and collaborative service delivery to youth in our
      community.
      For the past three years, MCCOY has been actively engaged in
      accomplishing this declared mission in cooperation with many others:
      youth service providers, youth, funding bodies, and interested citizens
      to name a few.
      We have met with a number of successes along the way, most notably the
      Summer Fun Line, the Metro Summer Bus Pass, and the development of ten
      neighborhood youth councils. A Providers Council and a Youth Coalition
      are building relationships that will hopefully bear great fruit in the
      years to come. The formation of The Community Academy, a pilot project
      directed at expelled students from local school systems, has come about
      as a result of MCCOY's efforts to mobilize community agencies in response
      to a pressing issue.
      McCoy is actively represented and working with numerous community
      collaborations where we regularly raise our voice to speak out for the
      inclusion of young people in both decision-making and program planning
      processes. One concrete example is a joint project undertaken in the
      United Northwest Area in partnership with The Junior League of
      Indianapolis and Community Partnerships with Youth from Fort Wayne,
      Indiana. As a team, these three organizations are working with
      neighborhood youth and adults to build a "Caring Neighborhood with Youth"
      , mobilizing the assets of young people and adults as partners to build a
      better neighborhood for all.
      Since its re-organization, MCCOY has established its unique niche
      within the community by refraining from direct service programming and
      focusing on what it does best: helping to identify youth needs, convening
      groups of individuals and organizations which can address those needs,
      and moving toward collaborative solutions. McCoy has only one interest:
      the well being of Marion County's young people.
      McCoy invites the support of The __ Company Foundation in the amount
      of $10,000.00 to support such activities as:
      ---- the co-ordination of youth leadership training and youth
      empowerment efforts at the neighborhood level by means of
      neighborhood-based youth councils; ---- the promotion of youth employment
      opportunities; ---- the facilitation of ongoing discussions regarding
      effective and efficient youth service delivery;
      ---- the provision of technical assistance and guidance to
      neighborhoods which seek positive youth-adult relationships;
      ---- the development of community-wide supports for the positive
      growth of all Marion County young people.
      In the last several years, the business and corporate community has
      recognized that the positive development of youth is directly related to
      the development of a competent workforce. Youth who are supported and
      encouraged by both a family and a society that values
      
      Them have a much greater likelihood of becoming productive and
      contributing members of adult society. While we have made significant
      inroads, there remains much to be done and it is clear that we cannot do
      it alone. We seek the financial support of the Foundation to help us be
      successful in creating the atmosphere in our community where young people
      can grow and develop well. Your contribution will enable us to both
      continue and expand the good work we have begun in making Indianapolis a
      city famous for its commitment to youth and families.
      In our fund raising efforts to date, we have received the support of
      local government, foundations, and corporations as well as the personal
      financial commitments of individual MCCOY Board members. We believe there
      is no more appropriate time to have a coordinated and collaborative
      effort to financially support the services MCCOY offers to the community
      as a whole.
      Thanking you in advance for your support, we remain,
      Sincerely,
      John T. Neighbours Philip B. Roby President Treasurer
      John F. Brandon Executive Director
    
  
