
  
  
    
      March 29, 1999
      Name Address City, ST Zip
      Dear Name:
      The 1999 Invest in Youth Campaign is in full swing. As a former board
      member, the success of the YMCA is still important to me. We must be able
      to reach all youth and families interested in values-based programs. The
      Invest in Youth campaign helps insure this.
      New initiatives in the inner-city are taking hold. The Urban Mission
      Branch is reaching out to middle school youth with programs based on
      caring, honesty, respect and responsibility for themselves and others.
      For some, these are very different messages from the ones heard in the
      street. They are learning to make positive choices concerning alcohol,
      tobacco and other drugs and to support each other when those choices are
      challenged.
      You have shared in the vision and the leadership of the YMCA of
      Greater Indianapolis. I now invite you to continue to support the mission
      and the message that is so important to building strong kids, strong
      families and strong communities. Please consider joining the Chairman's
      Roundtable with a gift of $1,000. I have enclosed a pledge card for your
      convenience. We would like to announce the success of this year's
      campaign at the Annual Meeting on April 27, so please return you pledge
      or gift within the next 30 days.
      Thank you.
      Sincerely,
      Richard H. Gilbert, Jr. Past Board Member YMCA of Greater
      Indianapolis
      
    
  
