
  
  
    
      March 17, 2000
      Name Address City, ST, Zip
      Dear Name:
      When Jerry was released from prison, he knew it would take hard work
      and determination to straighten out his life. He knew he had made a bad
      mistake, but despite his commitment to rebuilding his life, he just
      didn't count on the obstacles that would be thrown up in his path.
      Reality hit when he was unable to reconcile with his wife and ended up
      on the street. He went to the Center Township Trustee for food stamps
      until he could find a job and a place to live. The Trustee referred him
      to the Blue Triangle where he consulted Goodwill's Career Academy staff
      for job search assistance.
      Jerry's Goodwill caseworker found him a job immediately. But Jerry's
      troubles didn't end there. The seasonal construction job he obtained soon
      ended, and he returned to Career Academy for help once more. Unemployed,
      homeless and with a prison record, Jerry now faced going back to prison
      for failure to pay child support.
      It took some time and hard work, but with the help of Goodwill, Jerry
      was able to work out a payment plan with the prosecutor's office, find
      housing and conduct a more thorough job search.
      With unemployment at its lowest point in years in central Indiana,
      many people still have a hard time finding meaningful employment. Of the
      more than 42,000 people Goodwill served in 1999, over 5,000 of them have
      multiple barriers to finding and keeping a job. Some, like Jerry, are
      ex-offenders. Some are blind, deaf or have other physical disabilities.
      More than 100 were homeless.
      But Goodwill offers hope even to people with numerous obstacles to
      overcome, like Jerry. With a promising new job at a plastic injection
      molding manufacturer, his legal troubles in check and a safe place to
      live, Jerry can get on with the business of building a life for himself
      and contributing to his community. For as long as he needs it, Goodwill
      will continue to help.
      Your support of Goodwill will provide job training and placement
      services to help the hardest to serve in central Indiana find meaningful
      employment. And, with your assistance, Goodwill can help employers
      develop resources to keep workers on the job.
      Please make an investment in the stability of our community by sending
      a gift to Goodwill. Your generosity will help people help themselves.
      Sincerely,
      James M. McClelland President
    
  
