
  
  
    
      December 10, 1996
      Dear Mailhouse donor reminder:
      You and I have done some important work together.
      We've helped people break free of the welfare cycle. We've found ways
      for people with disabilities to enter the workforce. We've expanded
      Goodwill's proven methods to towns and neighborhoods where they are
      needed most.
      Of course, we've played different roles. You have helped make
      Goodwill's work possible with your previous support. Goodwill has devised
      the programs that turned your investment into results.
      Who has benefited from our partnership? Everyone has. When you and I
      help somebody find a job, one more person joins the ranks of tax payers,
      fewer tax dollars are spent on public assistance and businesses gain
      another consumer.
      There are a lot of barriers that keep people from working: physical
      and mental disabilities, history of welfare dependency and lack of
      education or self-esteem. And there are a lot of people who face these
      challenges every day of their lives. So our work must continue.
      Everyone benefits from the work we do together. Many people need our
      help.
      Please continue our important partnership. Support Goodwill with a
      generous donation today.
      Sincerely,
      James M. McClelland President
    
  
