
  
  
    
      November 15, 1994
      Dear ,
      Think of your greatest accomplishments. Think of the joy and success
      they bring to you and your loved ones.
      Michael Sims felt that way at age 39 -- the day he earned a job.
      Michael was born with cerebral palsy. Upon entering the work force, he
      discovered few job opportunities that seemed to match his abilities.
      For several years he performed packaging and clerical work. His most
      recent job lasted only a year before cut-backs eliminated his
      position.
      For 18 long months Michael could not find a job. He resorted to public
      assistance dollars to survive. Finally, Michael called Goodwill.
      At Goodwill, Michael's counselors felt that his personable demeanor
      could be a major attribute and identified for him a possible job-match
      where his people skills could shine.
      After three interviews, Michael proved that he was the right person
      for the job. As the Clubhouse Monitor at Bent Tree Apartments, he now
      provides customer service for 50 to 60 tenants each night.
      At last, he has found success in a job that he loves. Now his goals
      are set on moving up in the company.
      Every year, thousands of people come to Goodwill. Like Michael, they
      share two common characteristics. They face some barrier to employment
      and they want to work.
      With support from people like you, they can overcome their barriers
      and earn success and the self-sufficiency that comes with it. And then
      the pay-off begins for the entire community.
      Individual successes at Goodwill mean fewer persons receiving public
      support and more paying taxes. Last year, participants in Goodwill
      programs earned --and paid taxes on -- wages of nearly $3.5 million.
      Their successes at work also saved taxpayers more than three-quarters of
      a million dollars in public assistance.
      The savings are counted in more ways than dollars and cents, however.
      The families of the new wage earners may feel the accomplishment in terms
      of a house to live in, money to purchase food -- without food stamps --
      and the beginning of a family focused on success, not hopelessness.
      Won't you help make all of these successes possible? Please send the
      largest contribution you can comfortably make. Your gift will help give
      new meaning to the word success -- for people who have seldom had reason
      to use the word.
      Sincerely,
      James M. McClelland President
      P.S. Your gift will make a difference. For every dollar of public
      support Goodwill received last year, we returned $1.59 to the community
      in the form of earned wages and reduced public assistance payments.
    
  
