
  
  
    
      June 21, 1999
      Name Address City, ST Zip
      Dear ,
      Do you remember the combination of elation and apprehension you felt
      when you first left home? The young adults who leave Pleasant Run have
      those same feelings. Very few have family support to get them started.
      Many need furniture, linens and other basic necessities to begin lives on
      their own.
      To help them establish themselves in the community, the Pleasant Run
      Emancipation fund was begun in 1993 by private donors who wanted to
      provide a measure of financial support for those leaving our
      programs.
      Individuals who are being emancipated are eligible to receive up to
      $500 from the Fund if they formally apply and meet four requirements: 1.
      Release by the courts 2. Successful completion of all life skills tests
      3. Positive termination of his or her Pleasant Run program 4. Possession
      of a high school diploma or GED
      Proof of meeting these, two staff reference letters and an essay
      stating why they should receive a grant and how it will be used are all
      reviewed by a Pleasant Run panel, which determines if the applicant
      merits the funds.
      Such fund are often used for college tuition, vocational training or a
      deposit on an apartment.
      Because Pleasant Run is the only "family" for so many, our
      Emancipation Fund is one way we can help a young person take the first
      steps into his or her new life as an independent and productive
      adult.
      Without private donor support, this Fund doesn't exist. Please take a
      few minutes to send a donation to help one or more of our children
      successfully cross that threshold into the future.
      Sincerely,
      Mary Roth Executive Director
    
  
