
  
  
    
      It's hard to believe that the holiday season is only two months away.
      At Pleasant Run, Inc. we are making plans and arrangements for our
      children and families.
      Every year we seek companies, organizations and individuals to sponsor
      one or more of our families. These families are participants in our
      community-based programs. These programs focus on keeping the family
      together by providing counseling and other services to the entire family.
      After our caseworkers meet with these families and their children they
      often find they lack even the basic necessities such as cooking utensils,
      beds, cleaning supplies, etc. We meet these needs immediately. But, the
      holiday season is a particularly difficult time for these families. They
      do not have the resources necessary to purchase gifts or food for a
      holiday meal.
      We are asking you to consider sponsoring one of our families for this
      holiday season. If you are interested and would like more information,
      please contact Lisa Lusk or Marcia Whited at 693-9222. We would like to
      have families matched with sponsors non later than xxxx. Thank you for
      considering this opportunity to make this a memorable holiday season for
      a family in need.
      Sincerely,
    
  
