
  
  
    
      June 1, 1998 BOYS & Girls Club OF INDIANAPOLIS
      Dear Friend,
      It's summertime, so it must be time for CAMP! Yes, it's that time of
      the year -- the start of the Boys & Girls clubs of Indianapolis'
      Camp. Six weeks of learning and exploring, sports, arts, and fellowship.
      A time for a youngster to enjoy the fun and benefits of residential camp
      living, dedicated staff and instruction, and a chance to make special
      friends.
      
      I know you're committed to ensuring today's children have safe,
      healthy, and positive summer experiences. That's why I want you to learn
      more about the Super Summer Safari Camp.
      At Super Summer Safari Camp, there are daily sports, nature, and arts
      activities. In addition to the fun stuff, important life-skills such as
      self-esteem, leadership, and interpersonal cooperation are being
      developed. Please read the enclosed brochure for more information on the
      wonderful Super Summer Safari Camp!
      It costs $225 to send one child to camp. Many members of the Boys
      & Girls Clubs of Indianapolis can't afford to go to camp without
      financial assistance, and that's why we need you!
      Please make camp possible for all deserving Indianapolis children and
      send in a tax deductible contribution today in the enclosed envelope.
      Consider sponsoring 1, 2, or 3 children. No matter the size of the
      donation, please know that your gift will be appreciated and make a
      difference.
      Sincerely,
      Richard Dickinson
      P.S. You can make a difference in a child's life. Sponsor a child at
      the Boys & Girls Clubs of Indianapolis' summer camp today!
      
    
  
