
  
  
    
      February 26, 1999
      Dear ,
      Kids today face overwhelming pressures, everything from trouble at
      home to gangs and drugs. Youngsters often find themselves feeling
      alienated and alone.
      That's where the Boys & Girls Clubs of Indianapolis come in. We
      reach out to kids -- especially those from disadvantaged neighborhoods
      where the risks are highest. We give them a chance to realize their own
      potential by giving them a place where they can develop a sense of
      competence, of usefulness, a sense of belonging and of influence.
      To accomplish this, the five area Boys & Girls Clubs of
      Indianapolis must be open and available when the kids need them, with the
      staff and programs the kids need to reach and grow into responsible and
      caring citizens.
      This costs money. Money for programs, for equipment, and for repairs
      and improvements to club facilities. Your contribution last year of
      helped us get where we are today. We are counting on you now to help us
      get where we need to be tomorrow. Would you please consider a gift of the
      same in 1999?
      Please, give generously. The kids are depending on you.
      Respectfully,
      James Campbell President of the Board Deputy Chief, Indianapolis
      Police Department
      A United Way Agency
      Please detach and return in the enclosed envelope.
      
    
  
