
  
  
    
      MMM F_NAME L_NAME TITLE COMPANY ADDRESS CITY,ST ZIP March 4, 1999
      Dear LTR_NAME:
      CCI has come a long way in the last five years. We've worked hard to
      structrue the organization so that we've ready to move boldly into the
      next century, and I believe that we have an exciting and successful
      future ahead of us.
      One of the areas we've decided to focus on is development. It's clear
      that if we don't increase our base of private funding, we won't have the
      kind of control we need to ensure the continued success of our centers
      and the very important services they offer. In 1998, CCI served 31,484
      individuals right in their own backyards. Where else would that many
      people turn if CCI weren't there to help?
      The community initiatives committee is working with our development
      office to put together a long-range fundraising plan that will ultimately
      bring more money into our centers. This in turn will help us to increase
      and even improve the services we offer.
      With this in mind, I am asking each one of you to make a personal
      contribution of $50, $100 or even $1,000 to show that you believe in the
      work that we do and are willing to support it with both your time and
      your finances. This way when we go out to ask for community support and
      are asked about our board giving level, we can show our in-house
      commitment through 100% board participation. I also encourage you to seek
      additional support through your company, church, or service
      organization.
      I know that our staff and committee members will be happy to go with
      you to talk to these group if you need their help. We're at an exciting
      juncture and it won't be long until we start seeing solid results from
      our efforts. Your financial support of the development process is just
      one step in making CCI a stronger, more efficient and ultimately more
      effective federation of service providers. Please, make your contribution
      today.
      Sincerely,
      J.Chris Graffeo Chair
      P.S. If you have any questions, feel free to call Valery De Long at
      CCI, 638-3360 x23.
    
  
