
  
  
    
      July 30, 1999
      Dear Name:
      Question What do you get in 987,165 hours with 291people in 15
      locations?
      Answer 34,700 opportunities to change a life!
      This is exactly what happened in 1997 when Community Centers of
      Indianapolis provided its comprehensive, neighborhood-based services to
      individuals and families all over Marion County. And we can do even more
      in 1999 with your financial support! Just look at the range of services
      we offer:
      70,0001 career assistance for youth Preschool for young children
      School Age Child Care for and children and youth Access services such as
      emergency and holiday assistance for all ages Adult Day Care for seniors
      Senior Case Management Aids Education for youth and adults Senior Social
      Involvement Computer Training for youth, adults and seniors Senior
      Nutrition meal program Day Care for young children Social Development and
      Recreation for children, youth and adults. HIPPY (Home Instructional
      Program for Preschool Youngsters) for families. Stopover crises
      counseling for youth. In Home Services for adults and seniors.
      Transportation for youth and seniors
      
      CCI is a federation of 13 neighborhood-based multi-service centers
      (plus one affiliate) whose mission is to identify and meet the human
      service needs of the greater Indianapolis community in the most
      effective, efficient and comprehensive way possible. Better yet, most of
      these services occur in cooperation with private and public agencies from
      all over the city - CICOA The Access Network, Goodwill Industries,
      Indianapolis Housing Agency, City of Indianapolis, Indianapolis Private
      Industry Council, Family and Social Services administration, OTC, Indy
      Parks, and numerous community development corporations, neighborhood
      organizations, and churches, to name just a few.
      More than 34,000 people benefited from our services in 1997, and the
      final count for 1998 could be even higher. We're asking for a
      contribution in the amount of because you can't got a better bang for
      your buck than to support an organization that impacts so many lives in
      so many ways. Your gift will enable CCI to provide these and other
      necessary services at a neighborhood level, face-to-face, where it
      counts.
      Please, make a tax deductible gift to Community Centers of
      Indianapolis in 1999, and know that COMPANY is playing an important part
      in meeting the needs of its community. If you have any questions, please
      feel free to give us a call at 638-3360. We thank you for your
      consideration, and look forward to hearing from you.
      Sincerely,
      Earline S. Moore President
      Valery De Long Director of Development
      
    
  
