
  
  
    
      October 27, 1998
      Dear Name:
      Join us for the "Sale of the Century" at JCC Auction '99, on Saturday,
      November 13, 1999. The 9th annual JCC Auction will benefit the numerous
      scholarship programs of the Jewish Community Center of Indianapolis, a
      United Way agency. Because you are an organization that cares, you are
      invited once again to be an integral part of this fabulous event as a
      corporate sponsor for JCC Auction '99.
      We are so grateful for your generous contribution to last year's
      auction. Your continued participation is very important to the JCC, as we
      work to build partnerships between businesses and our not-for-profit
      agency. As a sponsor, you and your guests will have a special evening,
      knowing that your tax deductible contribution will help support
      preschool, childcare, senior and resettlement services, as well as
      quality cultural events in our community.
      Enclosed is a corporate sponsorship package that includes a sample of
      your ad from last year's auction book, current JCC market statistics and
      an overview of the many JCC programs that will be preserved and
      strengthened through your generous support.
      One of us will call you to discuss how your company can continue to be
      an important, highly visible partner with the JCC in support of our
      scholarship programs. If you have any questions, please feel free to call
      Myrna Weinberger at 251-9467, ext. 256. Thank you in advance for your
      consideration.
      Sincerely,
      Judy Laikin, Chair Auction '99 Sponsor Committee
    
  
