
  
  
    
      July 28, 1999
      Dear
      Join us for the "Sale of the Century" at JCC Auction '99, on Saturday,
      November 13, 1999. The 9th annual JCC Auction will benefit the numerous
      scholarship programs of the Jewish Community Center of Indianapolis, a
      United Way agency. Because you are an organization that cares, you are
      invited to become an integral part of this fabulous event by becoming a
      corporate sponsor for JCC Auction '99.
      The JCC would be very pleased to welcome your organization as a
      corporate sponsor. We are seeking to build partnerships between
      businesses and our not-for-profit agency. As a sponsor, you and your
      guests will have a special evening, knowing that your tax deductible
      contribution will help support preschool, childcare, senior and
      resettlement services, as well as quality cultural events in our
      community.
      Enclosed is a corporate sponsorship package that includes a sample
      auction book from last year's event, JCC market statistics and an
      overview of the many programs that will be preserved and strengthened
      through your generous support.
      One of us will call you to discuss how your company can become an
      important highly visible partner with the JCC in support of our
      scholarship programs. If you have any questions, please feel free to call
      Myrna Weinberger at 251-9467, ext. 256. Thank you in advance for your
      consideration.
      Sincerely, Judy Laikin, Chair Auction '99 Sponsor Committee
      
    
  
