
  
  
    
      
      Name Address City, State, Zip
      Dear Name,
      It's tough growing up today. We know that children do better when they
      have a network of caring adults to nurture and motivate them. When young
      people don't have that support, they need other resources for
      encouragement to guide them along the way. Big Sisters helps bridge that
      gap by providing children with the resources they need -- Big Sisters
      volunteers.
      Big Sisters are mentors and friends who empower girls to more fully
      reach their potential, experience life's opportunities and perhaps begin
      to dream. The relationships that are formed provide strong foundations
      from which healthy values and strong self-confidence can grow, helping
      youth become strong, independent adults of tomorrow.
      This year we will serve over 1,000 girls through our mentoring
      programs. This is an impressive number; but for each girl served, more
      are left unserved. Over 150 girls are currently waiting for a Big
      Sister.
      You can make an impact by supporting Big Sisters Annual Campaign and
      our $200,000 goal. If you are a regular contributor to the Annual
      Campaign, I encourage you to consider increasing your gift by 10%. If you
      have not supported Big Sisters in the past, please join me in doing so by
      completing and returning the enclosed pledge form.
      Early adolescence is the most vulnerable age for youth. But caring
      adults like you can reach out and help. It's the perfect time to make a
      world of difference.
      Sincerely,
      
      
    
  
