
  
  
    
      August 10, 1999
      Mr. Caring Philanthropy 01234 Giving Way Contribution, USA 56789
      Dear Mr. Philanthropy,
      "The urgency you feel to make changes is just the extent that change
      will be made. Do not sit this one out. Do not play it safe. Understand
      the world and change it where it needs to be changed... Make our society
      better. Make a world worthy of the children that your generation will
      bear." -- Carl Sagan
      You can help make positive changes in the lives of at-risk youth in
      central Indiana. We often hear about economic poverty, but what some of
      these young people are growing up with is emotional poverty-they have
      often given up on hope and the possibility of a successful future. With
      your help, we can change that.
      Many Little Sisters are preparing to go back to school this fall full
      of hope and with a positive outlook. Thanks to our Big Sisters
      volunteers, these young people are self-confident, believe in themselves
      and are beginning to realize their full potential. A recent study by
      Public/Private Ventures (PPV) showed that girls who had a Big Sister for
      just one year:
      reduced first-time drug use by 46% lowered school absenteeism by 52%
      cut violent behavior by 33% enhanced school performance showed improved
      peer and family relationships
      Former Little Sister Amy, now 18-years old, is a testament to the Big
      Sisters program.
      "I was matched with my Big Sister in June of 1992. Since then, she and
      I have grown very close and I have been able to experience lots of new
      things. We go to movies, dinner, concerts, and other stuff like that, but
      I have also been able to participate in charity events and fundraiser
      type things.
      Not only did I have a lot of fun with my Big Sister, but I learned a
      lot from her too. I have become more open-minded, more responsible, and,
      most importantly, I have gained a lot more self-confidence. I am very
      thankful to the Big Sisters program for allowing me this very special
      opportunity.
      In 1998, Big Sisters served 972 young people through its many
      programs. But the need is still great. Over 170 young people are still
      waiting for a mentor.
      You are an important part in making sure these young people are
      matched with caring adult mentors. Will you make a financial gift to Big
      Sisters in 1999 that will ensure that more young people receive the
      guidance they need, that more young people stay in school, stay off drugs
      and make good choices?
      Your contribution will be used to recruit and retain quality
      volunteers. It will also be used to help maintain the infrastructure that
      fosters and supports the development of effective relationships,
      including volunteer orientation and training and ongoing supervision and
      support by a professional staff. This year your gift can go farther!
      Gifts of $100 or more will be matched thanks to a special 25th
      Anniversary $100,000 Challenge Grant and will be placed in the Growth For
      Girls Fund. This fund will support the goal of having 550 mentoring
      relationships by the end of 1999 and 1,200 by the end of 2004.
      If you would like to find out more about the Big Sisters program,
      please call us, (317) 634-6102 and ask for Ellen Robinson. Thank you very
      much for your time, attention and consideration.
      Sincerely,
      Andrew T. Burns Patron Relations Chairperson
      P.S. When you give to Big Sisters, you can get 50% back! For a minimum
      contribution of $250, you become eligible for a 50% Indiana state tax
      credit through the Indiana Department of Commerce Neighborhood Assistance
      Program (NAP). A limited number of credits are available. To receive an
      application form, check the NAP box on the enclosed pledge card or call
      us, (317) 634-6102, ext. 20.
    
  
